A Guide to the Van Meter Family Papers, 1749-1870
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Van Meter Family Papers, 1749-1870
Library of Virginia
28128
4 cubic feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Woodrow Wilson Birthplace Foundation, Staunton, Virginia, 1973.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Van Meter family were prominent residents of Hardy County, (West) Virginia. Isaac Van Meter was born on 10 December 1757 at "Fort Pleasant." He married Bettie Inskeep (1763-1827) in Hardy County on 27 June 1780. They had thirteen children. Isaac Van Meter died at "Oldfields" on 13 December 1837. His oldest son was David Van Meter. He was born on 1 September 1784. He married Hannah Cunningham (d. 1878). David Van Meter died on 12 May 1871. Both Isaac and his son David were successful cattle and stock breeders in Hardy County.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1749-1870, of the Van Meter family of Hardy County, (West) Virginia, and Illinois, Ohio, and Kentucky. Most of the collection relates to the activities of Isaac Van Meter (1757-1837) and his son David Van Meter (1784-1871). Includes correspondence, accounts and receipts, and subject files.
The correspondence covers the period 1794 to 1869. Subjects include the Van Meter's involvement in the cattle and stock business, legal and financial matters, land sales, health, social activities, such as their involvement in the Presbyterian church, and other news of the family. There are a number of letters relating to David Van Meter's militia service during the War of 1812 while he was stationed near Norfolk. Also of interest are letters during the late 1820's on the topic of the education of David's children, including correspondence between him and their teacher. There is correspondence concerning state and national politics, including letters on the subject of the removal of deposits from the Bank of the United States. There are also letters written by John Inskeep Van Meter (1798-1875), David's brother, who was a member of the Ohio state legislature, and also served in the United States House of Representatives.
The subject files contain a variety of information on the family, including agreements, bonds, cattle and stock business papers, and estate papers. David Van Meter served as administrator or executor on a number of estates, including William Cunningham, Sr. (d. 1828), for whom there is a considerable amount of material. The subject files also contain fee bills, memorandum books, military service papers, plats and surveys, promissory notes, and tax tickets and receipts.
The collection also contains a large group of accounts and receipts, as well as oversized items.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1794-1869 (Box 1-2)
  - 1794 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1804 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1805 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1811 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1812 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1813 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1814 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1816 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1819 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1820 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1821 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1822 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1823 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1824 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1825 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1826 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1827 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1828 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1829 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1830 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1831 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1832 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1833 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1834 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1835 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1836 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1837 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1838 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1839 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1841 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1842 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1843 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 1844 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 1845 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 1847 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 1848 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 1849 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 1850 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 1851 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - 1852 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - 1854 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 1855 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 1856 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 1857 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - 1859 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - 1860 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1865 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1867 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1868 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1869 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1753-1870 (Box 2-3)
  - 1753, 1773, 1775 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1781 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1784 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1786 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1788 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1789 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1790 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1791 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1792 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1793 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1794 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1795 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1796 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1797 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1798 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1799 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1800 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1801 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1803 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 1804 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 1805 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 1806 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 1807 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - 1808 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - 1809 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - 1810 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - 1811 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - 1812 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 1813 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 1814 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 1815 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - 1816 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - 1817 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - 1818 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - 1819 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - 1820 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - 1821 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - 1822 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - 1823 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - 1824 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - 1825 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - 1826 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - 1827 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - 1828 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - 1829 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - 1830 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - 1831 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - 1832 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - 1833 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - 1834 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - 1835 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - 1836 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - 1837 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - 1838 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - 1839 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - 1840 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1841 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1842 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1844 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1845 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1846 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1847 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1848 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1849 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1850 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1851 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1852 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1853 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 1854 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 1855 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 1856 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - 1857 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - 1858 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - 1859 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - 1860 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - 1861 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - 1862 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - 1863 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - 1864 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - 1865 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - 1866 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - 1867 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - 1868 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - 1869 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - 1870 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - n.d. (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Subject Files. (Box 3-6)
  - Agreements, 1785-1853 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Assignments (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Bank Protests, 1850, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Bonds, 1798-1830 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Bonds and Appointment as Deputy Sheriff (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Bounty Land of Widow of George Webb, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Building Specifications (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Cattle/Stock Business Papers (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Circulars (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Clippings (Marriage Announcements) (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "The Comforts of Piety" by Jeremy Taylor (1831) (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Deeds, 1752-1853 (see also Oversize) (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Delinquent Lands (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Directions for Using Vaccine, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Estate of Mary Burch (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Estate of Thomas Crosby (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Estate of George Cunningham (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Estate of William Cunningham - Accounts and Receipts (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Estate of William Cunningham - Bonds (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Estate of William Cunningham - Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Estate of William Cunningham - Fee Bills (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Estate of William Cunningham - Inventory and Appraisement (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Estate of William Cunningham - Sales (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Estate of William Cunningham - Settelements (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Estate of William Cunningham - Suit Papers (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Estate of William Cunningham - Tax Tickets and Receipts (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Estate of Elizabeth Drake (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Estate of Abraham Hite (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Estate of Isaac Hite (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Estate of Neal McKinley (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Estate of John Oglevie (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Estate of George Rankin (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Estate of George Van Meter (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Estate of Henry Van Meter (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Estate of Isaac Van Meter (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
  - Estate of Jacob Van Meter (see also Oversize) (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Fee Bills - Assessor, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court,1786-1789 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, 1796-1799 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, 1800-1809 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, 1810-1811 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, 1812 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, 1813 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, 1814-1819 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, 1820-1829 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, 1830-1839 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, 1840-1849 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, 1850-1858 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Fee Bills - Clerks of Court, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Fee Bills - Commissioner of the Revenue, 1804-1859 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Fee Bills - Sheriff, 1789, 1800-1868 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Fee Bills - Surveyor, 1807, 1843-1858 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Fragments (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Land Entry (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Land Grant, 1785 (copy) (see also Oversize) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Land Grants - Northern Neck, 1749-1780 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - List of Deliquent Lands in Preston County, 1833 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lists and Valuations of Negroes (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Medical Prescription (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum and Account Book, 1816-1826 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Memorandum Book and Travel Diary, 1832 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Military Service Papers (see also Oversize) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Muster Fines, 1811-1852 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Oath of Allegiance (blank) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Order Granting Permission to Erect Dam, 1826 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Orders for Payment of Witnesses (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Orders for Payment or Goods, 1780-1868 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Plats and Surveys (see also Oversize) (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
  - Powers of Attorney, 1767-1838 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Promissory Notes (Box 5, Folder 19-21)
  - Receipts for Wheat Crop, 1840 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Relinquishments of Dower (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Report of Absences - University of Virginia, 1852 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Road and Bridge Papers (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Sale Bill, 1829 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Slave Bill of Sale, 1826 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Stock Certificate - North Branch Bridge Company, 1851 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Suit Papers (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1780-1781, 1787-1789 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1792, 1796-1798 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1800-1809 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1810-1815 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1816-1819 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1820-1829 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1830-1839 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1840-1849 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1850-1859 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1860-1869 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Will of Abraham Inskeep, Fayette County, Kentucky, 1850 (copy) (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Wrappers (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Oversize (Box 7)
  - Estate of Jacob Van Meter - Accounts (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Deeds, 1769-1824 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Land Grant, 1792 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Schedules of Pay, Forage, and Subsistence of Troops, 1814 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Survey, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 6)